Rachel Mathew

Email: rach235@yahoo.com

Phone: 214-604-3296

Personal Profile:

I'm a second degree nursing student pursuing my BSN at the University of Houston and a graduate from the University of Texas at Dallas with a Bachelor of Science degree in Biology. I have several years of experience as a hospital volunteer and have worked as a medical scribe. I'm passionate about patient care and believe in compassionate and efficient care. My goal is to care for patients that are at their most vulnerable place in life and to be a patient advocate and accountable member of the healthcare team. I have completed two semesters of nursing school.

Skills and Interests:

Motivational speaking

Fluent in English and Malayalam

Skilled with Computers (Typing, Microsoft office, Excel, PowerPoint)

Obtain and document vital signs, manage and document I&O, perform oral hygiene, bed baths, comfort positioning, turning, and participate in patient transfers from bed to chair or wheelchair. Have been checked off in nursing school lab on O2 delivery systems, incentive spirometry, manage SCD and TED hose, administer oral medication, IM, and SQ with faculty supervision.

Education:

Hebron High School August 2010 – May 2014

University of Texas at Dallas August 2014 – May 2018

Bachelor of Science in Biology

University of Texas at Dallas

August 2018-April 2019

Post Baccalaureate

University of Houston

January 2020- December 2021(Expected date)

Bachelor of Science in Nursing

2nd degree BSN

Awards and Honors:

Inducted into the National Society of Leadership and Success

NELA (National Engaged Leadership Award) from the National Society of Leadership and Success

UH College of Nursing Deans List for Spring 2020

Volunteer Experience:

Baylor Medical Center Irving (High School)

2 years

Baylor Medical Center Irving (College)

1 year

Volunteered in Surgical Department and aided staff with incoming patients

- Delivered blood work to labs and observed surgeries in the Operation Room.
- Volunteered in many areas such as Rehab, and other nursing floors throughout the hospital.

Clinical Experience:

Medical-Surgical Houston Methodist Sugarland Spring 2020

Pediatrics St. Peters Pre-school Spring 2020

Psychiatric Memorial Hermann Prevention Spring 2020

and Recovery Center

Community Outreach:

Third Ward Children's Health Fair at Trinity United Methodist Church Houston, TX Spring 2020

- Volunteered at Children's Health Fair in bringing awareness to healthcare disparities as well as providing information about health and wellness.

Research

Undergraduate Research in Molecular and Cellular Biology (Heme Signaling in Eukaryotic Cells)

(January 2018- May 2018)

- Worked with PhD students in Molecular Biology to help with researching the effects of neuronal cell degradation on the onset of Alzheimer's disease.
- Created research papers on neuronal cell degradation and the role of the aB peptide on Alzheimer's.
- Shadowed PhD students in the Natural Science Research Lab at UTD.

Work Experience

Medical Scribe with PhysAssist Scribes

(April 2017- August 2017)

- Worked closely with a Physician to transcribe all patient and provider information.
- Worked to serve the patient population of the Dallas area.

Building Staff in the Activity Center at the University of Texas at Dallas (April 2018 - December 2018)

- Worked to maintain the activity center, check equipment, and help students
- Worked in the control desk to manage activities of all student worker

CPR Certification

Adult and Child CPR/AED certified: Valid for 2 years. Conducted by the American Red Cross.

Issued on: 10/15/2019

Leadership Skills:

Secretary of the National Society of Leadership and Success at the University of Texas at Dallas (May 2017- January 2018)

- Presented and provided the organization with alternative methods for fundraising and social events
- Worked to improve and change the society's overall events and framework
 Participated in extending the society's chapter at UTD after a 3 year mark.

President of the National Society of Leadership and Success at the University of Texas at Dallas (January 2018- May 2018)

- Serve as the main contact with the National Office of the society
- Complete all paperwork and annual reports
- Work with the Advisor(s) to ensure that other Officers, Chairs, and members are informed about meetings and programs through phone and email reminders as well as emailing the minutes and notes of committee meetings.
- Serve as a liaison by maintaining communication and encouraging collaboration among other student organizations, campus departments, and administrators.
- Schedule and preside over regular meetings of the Executive Board. § Preside at The Society meetings.
- Prepare a report for each meeting.
- Work closely with the Advisor(s).
- Train new leaders that are replaced as a result of vacancies.
- Attend all events as deemed necessary by the Executive Board with approval of the Advisor(s).
- Hold an election discussion to go over proper procedures and questions for all elections as outlined by the Bylaws.

Student Advisor for the National Society of Leadership and Success (June 2018-December 2019)

- Advise current leaders and officers of the society in regards to meetings, training, and scheduling
- Work with faculty advisors to aid student officers in their role

Treasurer of Pre-Soma (Student Osteopathic Medical Association) Society at the University of Texas at Dallas (August 2017-May 2018)

Maintain the organization's funds and bank account

- Inform members about medical school requirements and osteopathic medical school admissions
- Educate members about osteopathic medicine and manipulative techniques
- Work with officers to plan meetings and actively participate to fundraise and volunteer Arise worship coordinator at Marthoma Church of Dallas Farmers Branch (2015-2017)
- Worked to change the order of worship and liturgy for youth service
- Enhanced and changed buildings in which people would worship Organized and lead the order of worship
- Coordinated the youth service on Sunday and maintained the order of worship

Organizations

Member of Health Occupations Student Association at the University of Texas at Dallas

August 2014- December 2016

Member of Alpha Epsilon Delta at the University of Texas at Dallas

August 2014- December 2016